{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "In this U.S. state, a team of death row inmates played baseball as the \"Alston's All- Stars\" to postpone their own execution date. This state's Fort Laramie served as a staging ground for army offensives during the Great Sioux [[SOOH]] Wars of the 1870s. While a territory, this modern state became the first to allow women to vote in its elections, leading to its nickname, the \"Equality State\". For ten points, name this state that, since 1890, has been governed from Cheyenne.",
      "answer": "Wyoming"
    },
    {
      "question": "A contingent of this European people populated the Haitian city of Cazale [[kah- SAL]] after they betrayed Napoleon's troops. Over 20,000 officers and other intelligentsia of these people were murdered by the NKVD in the Katyn [[kah-TEEN]] Forest Massacre. With Hungarian Michael Kovats [[KOH-vach]], a nobleman of this nationality named Casimir Pulaski [[poo-WAH-skee]] reformed the American Cavalry Corps. For ten points, name these people who's country was invaded on September 1, 1939 to begin World War Two.",
      "answer": "Poles"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Transnational Federal Government was formed in 2004 in this nation, which was led by Siad Barre [[SEE-add BAR-reh]] from 1969 until 1991. An American response to civil war in this nation turned disastrous when two Black Hawk helicopters were shot down. During the 2000s, this country was considered the home base of many pirates raiding shipping near the Gulf of Aden. For ten points, name this war-torn nation on the horn of Africa, once divided into British and Italian colonies.",
      "answer": "Somalia"
    },
    {
      "question": "The melody from this piece was used as Rhodesia's National Anthem during the 1970s, and was also played for German Olympians during the Cold War. Johannes Brahms quoted this melody in one of his symphonies, and the original composer borrowed the lyrics from a Friedrich Schiller poem. Today, this piece of music is used as the Anthem of Europe, and is the melody of the hymn Joyful, Joyful We Adore Thee. For ten points, name this piece of music, the finale of Beethoven's 9th Symphony.",
      "answer": "Ode to Joy"
    },
    {
      "question": "Faina Vakhreva was the wife of the ruler of this island, whose adopted brother commanded a panzer division during the Anschluss of Austria. Before moving to this island, its leader created the \"Gannan New Deal,\" where civilians could talk to him at a \"public information desk.\" A ruler of this island arrested the \"Rommel of the East,\" Sun Li-jen, under conspiracy charges during the KMT's White Terror. For ten points, Chiang Ching Kuo and his father Chiang Kai Shek both controlled what East Asian island country?",
      "answer": [
        "Taiwan",
        "Republic of China",
        "or ROC"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A toxic pool labeled for this blight is shown in a political cartoon where men labelled \"Mr. Careless\" and \"Anti-Vaccinationist\" fall off a cliff titled \"Misinformation.\" During the Siege of Fort Pitt, Governor-General Jeffrey Amherst oversaw the gift of several blankets infected with this disease to opposing Native Americans. Edward Jenner inoculated people against, for ten points, what disease that was eradicated in the 1970s?",
      "answer": [
        "Smallpox",
        "Variola Major",
        "or Variola Minor"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This league's color barrier was broken in 1947 by Japanese-American Wataru Misaka. A coach in this league, Steve Kerr, came under fire in 2020 due to his comments about Hong Kong and the role of the Chinese government. In 2009, the owner of this league's Los Angeles Clippers was sued by former star Elgin Baylor on the grounds of racial discrimination. For ten points, name this league which mourned the death of Kobe Bryant in January 2020.",
      "answer": "National Basketball Association or NBA"
    },
    {
      "question": "A region predominantly made of these geographical features called \"Al-Ahsa\" is known for producing high-quality bisht cloaks. One of these places, whose name translates to \"Field of Trees,\" was the site of the Oracle of Amon, which confirmed Alexander the Great as Pharaoh of Egypt. The Tuareg confederations used these geographical features as waypoints while on Trans-Saharan trade routes. Siwa in Egypt is an example of, for ten points, what fertile patches of land within deserts?",
      "answer": [
        "Oasis or Oases",
        "specifics like Siwa Oasis"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Like William Jennings Bryan, this man won a significant portion of electoral votes in multiple elections without becoming president. This man negotiated an end to the Nullification Crisis with his contemporary, John Calhoun. This Whig negotiated the admission of California into the Union three decades after accomplishing a similar feat with Missouri. For ten points, name this \"Great Compromiser\" from Kentucky.",
      "answer": "Henry Clay Sr. 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 6"
    },
    {
      "question": "The site of this city was purchased from the Mississauga by Lord Dorchester, though it remained unsettled until Governor John Graves Sicmoe established the town of York. John Strachan negotiated this town's surrender to the Americans in the War of 1812, after which it was the site of Government House on two occasions before it was moved to another location. William Lyons Mackenzie was the first mayor of this city until he abandoned it to lead the Upper Canada Rebellion. The Canadian National Railway built the CN Tower in, for ten points, which Ontario metropolis?",
      "answer": [
        "Toronto",
        "York before mentioned 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 6"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One ruler of this name became the last British monarch to lead an army in the field at the Battle of Dettingen [[deh-TIN-gehn]]. Robert Walpole became the first British prime minister under a ruler of this name after the South Sea Bubble burst. Another ruler of this name suffered from a mental illness believed to be porphyria [[por-\"FEAR\"-ee-ah]] and was king during the American Revolution. For ten points, give this name of four 18th and 19th- century British monarchs.",
        "answer": [
          "George",
          "George I",
          "or George II",
          "or George III"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The four Georges on the British throne were all from a dynasty named for this German state, which came to power after the death of Queen Anne.",
        "answer": "Hanover"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The third-place finisher in this U.S. election year suffered a stroke a year prior to it, leading to his poor performance. The Tertium Quids [[TER-shum KWIDS]] were represented by that man, William H. Crawford, in this election year. This election year saw the House of Representatives swing one man's electoral votes to the eventual winner in order to keep a Tennessee politician from winning office. For ten points, name this election year in which John Quincy Adams defeated Andrew Jackson thanks to the \"corrupt bargain.\"",
        "answer": "Election of 1824"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The House of Representatives was legally justified in choosing the winner of the election due to this amendment to the Constitution, which clarified electoral procedure after the chaos of the elections of 1796 and 1800.",
        "answer": "Twelfth Amendment or Amendment Twelve"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A biography of this ruler was written by Xenophon [[ZEE-noh-fohn]], who described this ruler being raised by a shepherd after his grandfather ordered him killed. According to Herodotus [[heh-ROD-oh-tus]], this king died fighting the Scythian queen Tomyris [[TOM-i- riss]]. A namesake cylinder celebrates this king’s defeat of the Babylonian king Nabonidus [[NAB-o-ni-dus]]. For ten points, name this ruler of the city of Anshan and founder of the Persian Empire.",
        "answer": [
          "Cyrus the Great",
          "Cyrus II"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "According to Herodotus, Cyrus was the grandson of Astyages [[AHS-tyah-GEEZ]], a king of these people. This Iranian people earlier allied with the Babylonians to destroy the Assyrian Empire.",
        "answer": "Medes or Median Empire 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 6"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Mehdi Bazargan resigned to protest the beginning of this event, which concluded with the signing of the Algiers Accords. The disastrous Operation Eagle Claw attempted to rescue victims of this event. This crisis ended within minutes of the inauguration of Ronald Reagan as U.S. president, following a 444 day period of imprisonment for its victims. For ten points, identify this diplomatic crisis that began when revolutionary students stormed a U.S. embassy in a Middle Eastern capital.",
        "answer": [
          "Iran Hostage Crisis",
          "Tehran Hostage Crisis",
          "descriptive answers"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the middle of the crisis, a war broke out between Iran and neighboring Iraq, which at the time was led by this expansionist Arab nationalist politician who later invaded Kuwait, sparking the Persian Gulf War.",
        "answer": "Saddam Hussein"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A precursor to this period of history was the wartime Port Royal Experiment. The only two-term leader during this period vetoed much of the legislation that was sent to him, but several bills were overridden by the Radical Republicans. During this period, the Enforcement Act was signed into law by President Ulysses S. Grant to counter the nascent Ku Klux Klan. For ten points, name this period of rebuilding that occurred immediately following the Civil War.",
        "answer": "Reconstruction era"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This man was elected president in 1876 in a heavily-contested race. The back-door compromise that assured him the presidency promised the effective end of Reconstruction.",
        "answer": "Rutherford Birchard Hayes"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Due to an alleged prophecy given by Jan Hus [[YAHN HOOS]], this man is often depicted with a swan. Scottish artist Joseph Noel Paton depicted this man at Erfurt discovering the doctrine of sola fide [[SOH-luh FEE-deh]]. This man was painted on several occasions by his friend and neighbor, Lucas Cranach [[KRAH-nahk]] the Elder, the court painter to the Elector of Saxony. For ten points, name this theologian and seminal figure in the Protestant Reformation who was often depicted in contemporary art.",
        "answer": "Martin Luther"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Hundreds of thousands of copies of Luther's Ninety-Five Theses were produced by this pioneering printer who developed the movable-type printing press.",
        "answer": "Johannes Gutenberg or Johannes Gensfleisch zur Laden zum Gutenberg 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 6"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this project, General Leslie Groves undertook a propaganda campaign to prevent \"loose talk\" by its participants. Despite his acts of treason, Klaus Fuchs [[FYOOKS]] was a key component on this project's development but later served nine years in prison for his actions. Because of his study and understanding of fast neutrons, Robert Oppenheimer was a prime member of this project. For ten points, name this top-secret U.S. project which developed the atomic bomb.",
        "answer": [
          "Manhattan Project",
          "Development of Substitute Materials"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which New Mexico city was home to much of the Manhattan Project and today houses a museum dedicated to the project?",
        "answer": "Los Alamos"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "US army officer Henry Schneider revealed that this company provided a third of all trucks in the Wehrmacht through their Cologne plant which was confiscated in 1941. In the 1920s, this company attempted to set up a free state in Brazil in order to dodge the British monopoly on rubber. While not invented by this company's leader, the assembly line was popularized in the car factories of this company. For ten points, name this American based car company famous for its production of Model T's.",
        "answer": "Ford Motor Company"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "While Detroit is known as the \"Motor City\", Ford's headquarters and the Henry Ford museum are located in what Michigan city, which was exposed in James M. Loewen's Sundown Towns for aggressively excluding Black migrants?",
        "answer": "Dearborn, Michigan"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "United States Generals",
      "prompt": "Name the U.S. general who...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was appointed to lead the Continental Army in the Revolutionary War.",
          "answer": "George Washington"
        },
        {
          "question": "Turned down the offer to lead Union troops to command the opposing Army of Northern Virginia instead.",
          "answer": "Robert Edward Lee"
        },
        {
          "question": "Declared \"I shall return\" after fleeing the Philippines to avoid Japanese capture in 1942.",
          "answer": "Douglas MacArthur"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was sent to Mexico in an attempt to capture the revolutionary Pancho Villa [[VEE- yah]].",
          "answer": "John \"Black Jack\" Pershing or John Joseph Pershing"
        },
        {
          "question": "Created the Anaconda Plan and served in the War of 1812 and the Mexican- American War.",
          "answer": "Winfield Scott"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the last to achieve the rank of Five Star General, second in command to Eisenhower during the Liberation of France.",
          "answer": "Omar Bradley Omar Nelson Bradley"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the leader of all coalition forces during Operation Desert Storm in the Persian Gulf War.",
          "answer": "\"Stormin'\" Norman Schwarzkopf or Herbert Norman Schwarzkopf, Jr."
        },
        {
          "question": "Was named for a South American liberator and died commanding troops on Okinawa, becoming the highest-ranking U.S. officer to die from enemy fire in World War Two.",
          "answer": "Simon Bolivar Buckner Jr."
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Regarding what some call the \"first global war\", name the...",
      "prompt": "Answer these questions about Regarding what some call the \"first global war\", name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Century in which the Seven Years' War occurred.",
          "answer": [
            "18th Century",
            "1700s"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "English name for the North American theater of the Seven Years' War.",
          "answer": "French and Indian War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Treaty which ended the Seven Years' War which shares its name with the treaty which ended the Revolutionary War.",
          "answer": [
            "Treaty of Paris",
            "Treaty of 1763"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City near the Plains of Abraham, where both James Wolfe and Louis Montcalm died.",
          "answer": "Quebec City or Ville de Québec"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Elder\" British prime minister credited for most of the victories during the Annus Mirabilis [[meer-AH-bih-liss]].",
          "answer": "William Pitt the Elder"
        },
        {
          "question": "Victorious general at Plassey who, with Warren Hastings, established British hegemony [[heh-JEH-moh-nee]] in India.",
          "answer": [
            "Robert Clive",
            "Clive of India"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City at the center of the French East India Company seized by the British in 1761.",
          "answer": [
            "Pondicherry",
            "Puducherry"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Naval victory near St. Nazaire where the Comte de Conflans [[KOHMT duh cohn- FLAHN]] lost to Edward Hawke's fleet near the Bay of Biscay.",
          "answer": "Battle of Quiberon ] Bay 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 6"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Reign of Suleiman the Magnificent",
      "prompt": "Concerning the reign of Suleiman the Magnificent, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Empire which he ruled.",
          "answer": [
            "Ottoman Empire or Ottomans",
            "Ottoman Turks"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Austrian capital city he besieged in 1529.",
          "answer": "Vienna or Wien"
        },
        {
          "question": "Serbian capital he razed in 1521.",
          "answer": [
            "Belgrade",
            "Beograd"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Island off the coast of Anatolia ruled by the Knights of St. John which he captured.",
          "answer": [
            "Rhodes",
            "Rodos"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Persian dynasty against which he conducted a prolonged campaign and later negotiated the Peace of Amasya [[ah-MAH-syah]].",
          "answer": "Safavid ] Dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "European kingdom which entered an \"unholy\" alliance with Suleiman.",
          "answer": "Kingdom of France or Royaume de France"
        },
        {
          "question": "1526 battle in which Suleiman's forces devastated the armies of Hungary, Bohemia, and Bavaria.",
          "answer": "Battle of Mohács ]"
        },
        {
          "question": "Father of Suleiman known as \"the Grim\" who annexed the Mamluk sultanate.",
          "answer": [
            "Selim I or Selim the Grim",
            "or Selim the Resolute",
            "or Selim the Mean 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 6"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Following the U.S. Invasion of Grenada, the Edward Seaga-led Labour Party won every seat in this nation's elections due to boycotts by the People's National Party. Back to Africa proponent Marcus (20 pts)",
        "Garvey was from this island nation, which saw multiple \"Maroon Wars\" against the British government. The destruction of Port (10 pts)",
        "Royal by a 17th-century earthquake led to the founding of, for ten points, which Caribbean nation's capital of Kingston?"
      ],
      "answer": "Republic of Jamaica or Jumieka"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The so-called \"Land Pirate,\" John Murrell, faced allegations of starting one of these events along the Mississippi River in a namesake \"Excitement.\" The testimony of George Wilson and Joe LaRoche quashed another of these events planned by a man known as (20 pts)",
        "Telemaque [[teh-leh-MAHK]] in Charleston. One of these events in Southampton, Virginia was suppressed at Belmont (10 pts)",
        "Plantation. For ten points, name these uprisings, one of which was led by Nat Turner."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Slave Rebellion",
        "equivalents like Slave Uprising",
        "specific answers like \"Denmark Vesey's Revolt\"",
        "Nat Turner's Revolt",
        "\"Enslaved Person\" in place of \"Slave\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This merchant was taken to court after his ship, the Liberty, was captured and he was accused of not paying fees under Townshend Acts. This colonial leader chaired a committee that demanded the removal of British troops following the (20 pts)",
        "Boston Massacre. This protégé of Samuel Adams served as the first governor of (10 pts)",
        "Massachusetts. For ten points, name this president of the Continental Congress who provided the first and largest signature on the Declaration of Independence."
      ],
      "answer": "John Hancock"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The crowning of Joseph Bonaparte led the First Junta [[HOON-tuh]] of this city to depose Viceroy Hidalgo de Cisneros [[sis-NEH-ros]] as part of the May Revolution. A women's movement in this city marched in support of those who \"disappeared\" during the (20 pts)",
        "Dirty War. This city's Plaza de Mayo and Casa Rosada presidential palace were bombed by its own air force following a pro-Juan (10 pts)",
        "Peron demonstration. The capital of the Viceroyalty of Rio de La Plata was, for ten points, what largest city in Argentina?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Buenos Aires",
        "Autonomous City of Buenos Aires",
        "or Ciudad Autónoma de Buenos Aires 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 6"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this civilization’s archaic period, the Battle of Alalia allowed its expansion to the Tyrrhenian [[tih-REE-nyen]] Sea. According to legend, twelve cities from this ancient civilization formed an eponymous (20 pts)",
        "league founded by Tachron [[TAH-kron]]. Alleged to have begun during the Iron Age with the Villanova (10 pts)",
        "culture, for ten points, what kingdom in ancient Italy was assimilated into Roman society in a series of eponymous wars?"
      ],
      "answer": "Etruscan civilization"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Ottoman Empire entered this conflict on the eventual losing side during the Pruth River Campaign. The Treaty of Nystad [[NEE-stad]] allowed the winning side of this war to seize the land to construct a new capital on the Gulf of (20 pts)",
        "Finland. The Battle of Poltava [[pohl-TAH-vuh]] during this conflict ended an invasion of (10 pts)",
        "Russia by King Charles XII [[the twelfth]]. For ten points, name this conflict where Russia under Peter the Great ended the golden age of the Swedish Empire."
      ],
      "answer": "Great Northern War"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A November 2021 prison riot in this nation's Litoral Penitentiary led to a call for a state of emergency by President Guillermo Lasso. Wikileaks founder Julian Assange (20 pts)",
        "was given asylum in this nation's embassy by then-president Rafael Correa [[kor-REH-ah]]. Anti-Lenin Moreno riots led to a government relocation to (10 pts)",
        "Guayaquil [[\"why\"-YAH-keel]] in, for ten points, what Andean nation governed from Quito?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Republic of Ecuador",
        "República del Ecuador",
        "or Republic of the Equator,",
        "Ikwadur Ripuwlika",
        "or Chawpipacha Ripuwlika",
        "Ekuatur Nunka"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this state, an indoor concert by hair metal band Great White led to a fire in West Warwick which killed one hundred attendees. In 2015, the governor of this state proposed a luxury tax on second homes which the media dubbed the \"Taylor Swift (20 pts)",
        "Tax\" due to her having beachfront property there. That governor of this state, Gina Raimondo, resigned to become Joe Biden's Secretary of Commerce. The words \"Providence (10 pts)",
        "Plantations\" were dropped from the name of, for ten points, which New England state?"
      ],
      "answer": "Rhode Island 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 6"
    }
  ]
}